My talk today is about something
حديثي اليوم حول شيء
maybe a couple of you have already heard about.
ربما إثنان منكم سمعوا به من قبل.
It's called the Arab Spring.
يُسمى الربيع العربي.
Anyone heard of it?
هل سمع به أحد من قبل؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So in 2011, power shifted,
إذن في 2011، تحولت القوة،
from the few to the many,
من القلائل إلى الكثر،
from oval offices to central squares,
من المكاتب البيضاوية إلى الميادين الرئيسية،
from carefully guarded airwaves
من موجات أثير محروسة بعناية
to open-source networks.
إلى شبكات مفتوحة المصدر.
But before Tahrir was a global symbol of liberation,
لكن قبل أن كان التحرير رمزا عالميا للتحرر،
there were representative surveys
كانت هناك استبيانات تمثيلية
already giving people a voice
أعطت الناس صوتا
in quieter but still powerful ways.
بهدوء ولكن بوسائل قوية.
I study Muslim societies around the world at Gallup.
أدرس المجتمعات الإسلامية حول العالم في غالوب.
Since 2001,
منذ 2001،
we've interviewed hundreds of thousands of people --
حاورنا مئات آلاف من الأشخاص --
young and old, men and women,
صغارا وكبارا ورجالا ونساءا،
educated and illiterate.
متعلمين وأميين.
My talk today draws on this research
يتطرق حديثي اليوم عن هذا البحث
to reveal why Arabs rose up
ليكشف لماذا انتفض العرب
and what they want now.
وماذا يريدون الآن.
Now this region's very diverse,
الآن هذه المنطقة متنوعة جدا،
and every country is unique.
وكل بلد فريد بذاته.
But those who revolted
لكن أولائك الذين ثاروا
shared a common set of grievances
تقاسموا مجموعة مشتركة من الآلام
and have similar demands today.
ولديهم اليوم مطالب مشابهة.
I'm going to focus a lot of my talk on Egypt.
سأركز كثيرا في حديثي عن مصر.
It has nothing to do with the fact that I was born there, of course.
بالطبع، ليس لذلك أي صلة بواقع أنني ولدت هناك.
But it's the largest Arab country
لكنها أكبر بلد عربي
and it's also one with a great deal of influence.
وهي كذلك بلد له الشيئ الكثير من التأثير.
But I'm going to end by widening the lens to the entire region
لكن سأنهي عبر توسيع العدسة لكل المنطقة
to look at the mundane topics
لننظر للمواضيع البديهية
of Arab views of religion and politics
حول رؤى العرب في الدين والسياسة
and how this impacts women,
وكيف يؤثر ذلك على النساء
revealing some surprises along the way.
كاشفين بعض المفاجآت خلال الطريق.
So after analyzing mounds of data,
إذن بعد تحليل أكوام من البيانات،
what we discovered was this:
ما اكتشفناه كان هذا:
Unemployment and poverty alone
البطالة والفقر لوحدهما
did not lead to the Arab revolts of 2011.
لم يؤديا للانتفاضات العربية في 2011.
If an act of desperation by a Tunisian fruit vendor
إذا كان عمل يائس من قبل بائع فواكه تونسي
sparked these revolutions,
أشعل هذه الثورات،
it was the difference between what Arabs experienced
كان الفرق بين ما اختبره العرب
and what they expected
وما توقعوه
that provided the fuel.
هو الذي وفر الوقود.
To tell you what I mean,
لأخبركم عما أقصد،
consider this trend in Egypt.
خذوا بعين الاعتبار هذه النزعة في مصر.
On paper the country was doing great.
على الورق كانت البلاد تبلي بلاءا حسنا.
In fact, it attracted accolades
في الحقيقة، جلبت الاطراءات
from multinational organizations
من شركات متعددة الجنسيات
because of its economic growth.
بسبب نموها الاقتصادي.
But under the surface was a very different reality.
لكن تحت السطح هناك حقيقة مغايرة تماما.
In 2010, right before the revolution,
في 2010، قبل الثورة تماما،
even though GDP per capita
رغم أن متوسط دخل الفرد من الناتج المحلي الإجمالي
had been growing at five percent for several years,
كان ينمو بخمسة بالمئة لعدة سنوات،
Egyptians had never felt worse about their lives.
لم يشعر المصريون بأسوء من ذلك فيما يتعلق بحياتهم.
Now this is very unusual,
الآن هذا غير مألوف جدا،
because globally we find that, not surprisingly,
لأنه على مستوى العالم نجد أنه ومن غير المفاجئ،
people feel better as their country gets richer.
يشعر الناس بتحسن عندما يصبح بلدهم أغنى.
And that's because they have better job opportunities
وذلك لأنه لديهم فرص عمل أفضل
and their state offers better social services.
وتعرض دولتهم خدمات اجتماعية أفضل.
But it was exactly the opposite in Egypt.
لكن كان العكس تماما في مصر.
As the country got more well-off,
بينما تصبح الدولة أفضل ماديا،
unemployment actually rose
ارتفعت في الحقيقة البطالة
and people's satisfaction
وتراجع بسرعة رضاء الناس
with things like housing and education plummeted.
عن أشياء مثل الإسكان والتعليم.
But it wasn't just anger at economic injustice.
لكن لم يكن فقط غضبا على عدم العدالة الاقتصادية.
It was also people's deep longing for freedom.
كان أيضا توق الناس العميق للحرية.
Contrary to the clash of civilizations theory,
خلافا لنظرية صدام الحضارات،
Arabs didn't despise Western liberty,
لم يمقت العرب الحرية الغربية،
they desired it.
لقد رغبوها.
As early as 2001,
ومنذ 2001،
we asked Arabs, and Muslims in general around the world,
سألنا العرب والمسلمين عموما حول العالم،
what they admired most about the West.
عما عشقوه أكثر في الغرب.
Among the most frequent responses
من ضمن الإجابات الأكثر شيوعا
was liberty and justice.
كانت الحرية والعدالة.
In their own words to an open-ended question
نقلا عن كلامهم نفسه عن سؤال ذو إجابة مفتوحة
we heard, "Their political system is transparent
سمعنا: "نظامهم السياسي شفاف
and it's following democracy in its true sense."
ويتبع الديمقراطية في معناها الصحيح"
Another said it was "liberty and freedom
قال آخر بأنه كانت: "الانعتاق والحرية
and being open-minded with each other."
وانفتاح الذهن تجاه بعضهم البعض."
Majorities as high as 90 percent and greater
أغلبية مرتفعة لحد 90 بالمئة وأكثر
in Egypt, Indonesia and Iran
في مصر وأندونيسيا وإيران
told us in 2005
أخبرونا في 2005
that if they were to write a new constitution
أنهم إذا كانوا سيكتبون دستورا
for a theoretical new country
لبلد جديد افتراضي
that they would guarantee freedom of speech
كانوا سيضمنون حرية التعبير
as a fundamental right,
حقا أساسيا،
especially in Egypt.
خاصة في مصر.
Eighty-eight percent said moving toward greater democracy
قال ثمانية وثمانون بالمئة بأن التوجه نحو ديمقراطية أكثر
would help Muslims progress --
كان سيساعد المسلمين في التقدم --
the highest percentage of any country we surveyed.
أعلى نسبة مئوية لأي بلد مسحناه.
But pressed up against these democratic aspirations
لكن في مواجهة هذه الطموحات الديمقراطية
was a very different day-to-day experience,
كانت هناك تجربة يومية مختلفة جدا،
especially in Egypt.
خاصة في مصر.
While aspiring to democracy the most,
رغم توقهم لأقصى درجة للديمقراطية،
they were the least likely population in the world
كانوا أقل سكان في العالم
to say that they had actually voiced their opinion
يقولون بأنهم أوصلوا آرائهم بالفعل
to a public official in the last month --
لمسؤول حكومي في الشهر الماضي --
at only four percent.
بأربعة في المئة فقط.
So while economic development made a few people rich,
إذن بينما جعلت التنمية الاقتصادية قلة من الناس أغنياء،
it left many more worse off.
تركت كثيرا جدا أفقر.
As people felt less and less free,
كما شعر الناس بأقل وأقل حرية،
they also felt less and less provided for.
حسّوا أيضا بأقل وأقل عناية.
So rather than viewing their former regimes
لذلك عوض النظر لأنظمتهم السابقة
as generous if overprotective fathers,
بصفتها كريمة وكآباء مفرطي الحماية،
they viewed them as essentially prison wardens.
نظروا إليهم بصفتهم حُراس السجن.
So now that Egyptians have ended Mubarak's 30-year rule,
لذلك الآن بعد إنهاء المصريين لحكم مبارك لثلاثين سنة،
they potentially could be
من المحتمل أن يكونوا
an example for the region.
مثالا للمنطقة.
If Egypt is to succeed
إذا قُدّر لمصر النجاح
at building a society based on the rule of law,
في بناء مجتمع ينبني على حكم القانون،
it could be a model.
يمكن أن تكون نموذجا.
If, however,
وإذا من ناحية أخرى
the core issues that propelled the revolution aren't addressed,
لم يقع التصدي للقضايا الجوهرية التي دفعت بالثورة،
the consequences could be catastrophic --
يمكن أن تكون النتائج كارثية --
not just for Egypt,
ليس فقط لمصر،
but for the entire region.
بل للمنطقة كلها.
The signs don't look good, some have said.
لا تبدو الإشارات جيدة حسب قول البعض.
Islamists, not the young liberals that sparked the revolution,
الإسلاميون وليس الليبراليون الشباب الذين أشعلوا فتيل الثورة،
won the majority in Parliament.
فازوا بالأغلبية في البرلمان.
The military council
المجلس العسكري
has cracked down on civil society and protests
قمع المجتمع المدني والمظاهرات
and the country's economy continues to suffer.
ويستمر اقتصاد البلاد في المعاناة.
Evaluating Egypt on this basis alone, however,
لكن تقييم مصر على هذه الأساس لوحده
ignores the real revolution.
يتجاهل الثورة الحقيقية.
Because Egyptians are more optimistic
لأن المصريين أكثر تفاؤلا
than they have been in years,
مما كانوا عليه في سنوات مضت،
far less divided on religious-secular lines
أقل انقساما بكثير حول خطوط التماس الدينية العلمانية
than we would think
مما كنا سنتوقع
and poised for the demands of democracy.
ومهيئين لمطالب الديمقراطية.
Whether they support Islamists or liberals,
سواءا كانوا يدعمون الإسلاميين أو الليبراليين،
Egyptians' priorities for this government are identical,
أولويات المصريين لهذه الحكومة متطابقة،
and they are jobs, stability and education,
وهي الوظائف والاستقرار والتعليم،
not moral policing.
وليس ضبط الأخلاق.
But most of all,
لكن الأهم من كل ذلك،
for the first time in decades,
لأول مرة منذ عقود
they expect to be active participants, not spectators,
يتوقعون أن يكونوا مشاركين نشيطين وليس متفرجين،
in the affairs of their country.
في شؤون البلد.
I was meeting with a group of newly-elected parliamentarians
كنت في لقاء مع برلمانيين منتخبين حديثا
from Egypt and Tunisia
من مصر وتونس
a couple of weeks ago.
منذ أسبوعين.
And what really struck me about them
وما أثار ذهولي حولهم
was that they weren't only optimistic,
كان أنهم لم يكونوا فقط متفائلين،
but they kind of struck me as nervous,
ذهلني توترهم،
for lack of a better word.
لانعدام كلمة أفضل.
One said to me,
قال أحدهم لي:
"Our people used to gather in cafes to watch football" --
"تعوّد الناس الاجتماع في المقاهي لمشاهدة كرة القدم" --
or soccer, as we say in America --
أو "سوكر" كما نسميها في أمريكا --
"and now they gather to watch Parliament."
والآن يجتمعون لمشاهدة البرلمان."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"They're really watching us,
"إنهم يشاهدوننا حقا،
and we can't help but worry
ولا نستطيع إلا أن نقلق
that we're not going to live up to their expectations."
بأننا لن نسمو لمستوى توقعاتهم."
And what really struck me
وما ذهلني حقا
is that less than 24 months ago,
هو أنه منذ أقل من 24 شهرا،
it was the people that were nervous
كان الناس هم المتوترون
about being watched by their government.
من مراقبة حكومتهم لهم.
And the reason that they're expecting a lot
وسبب توقعهم الشيء الكثير
is because they have a new-found hope for the future.
هو أنهم لديهم أملا حديث الوجود في المستقبل.
So right before the revolution
إذن قبل الثورة تماما
we said that Egyptians had never felt worse about their lives,
قلنا أن المصريين لم يشعروا بأسوأ من ذلك حول حياتهم،
but not only that, they thought their future would be no better.
لكن ليس ذلك فقط، توقعوا أن مستقبلهم لم يكن بإمكانه أن يصبح أفضل.
What really changed after the ouster of Mubarak
ما تغير فعلا بعد الاطاحة بمبارك
wasn't that life got easier.
لم يكن ان الحياة أصبحت أسهل.
It actually got harder.
لقد أصبحت أكثر صعوبة في الحقيقة.
But people's expectations for their future
لكن توقعات الناس لمستقبلهم
went up significantly.
ارتفعت بشكل ملحوظ.
And this hope, this optimism,
وهذا الأمل وهذا التفاؤل
endured a year of turbulent transition.
تحمّل سنة انتقالية مضطربة.
One reason that there's this optimism
سبب واحد لوجود هذا التفاؤل
is because, contrary to what many people have said,
هو أنه بسبب عكس ما قاله عديد الأشخاص،
most Egyptians think things really have changed in many ways.
معظم المصريين يعتقدون أن الأمور قد تغيرت فعلا في نواح عديدة.
So while Egyptians were known
لذلك بينما عُرف المصريون
for their single-digit turnout
بنسبة إقبال أقل من عشرة في المئة
in elections before the revolution,
في الانتخابات قبل الثورة،
the last election had around 70 percent voter turnout --
الانتخابات الأخيرة حققت حوالي 70 بالمئة نسبة إقبال الناخبين --
men and women.
رجالا ونساءا.
Where scarcely a quarter believed in the honesty of elections in 2010 --
حيث أن بالكاد الربع اعتقدوا في نزاهة الانتخابات في 2010 --
I'm surprised it was a quarter --
أنا متفاجئة لكونها ربعا --
90 percent thought that this last election was honest.
90 بالمئة اعتقدوا أن هذه الانتخابات الأخيرة كانت نزيهة.
Now why this matters
الآن ما أهمية ذلك
is because we discovered a link
لأننا اكتشفنا رابطا
between people's faith in their democratic process
بين إيمان الناس بعمليتهم الديمقراطية
and their faith that oppressed people
وإيمانهم أن الناس المضطهدين
can change their situation
يمكنهم تغيير وضعيتهم
through peaceful means alone.
عبر الوسائل السلمية لوحدها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now I know what some of you are thinking.
الآن أعرف ما يفكر فيه بعضكم.
The Egyptian people,
الشعب المصري،
and many other Arabs who've revolted and are in transition,
والعديد من العرب الآخرين الذين ثاروا والذين في وضع انتقالي
have very high expectations of the government.
لديهم توقعات عالية جدا للحكومة.
They're just victims of a long-time autocracy,
إنهم فقط ضحايا لحكم فردي طويل المدى،
expecting a paternal state
يتوقعون دولة أبوية
to solve all their problems.
تحلّ كل مشاكلهم.
But this conclusion would ignore
لكن هذا الاستنتاج كان يتجاهل
a tectonic shift taking place in Egypt
تحولا تكتونيا يقع في مصر
far from the cameras in Tahrir Square.
بعيدا عن الكاميرات في ميدان التحرير.
And that is Egyptians' elevated expectations
وهو أن توقعات المصريين العالية
are placed first on themselves.
تنصبّ أولا على أنفسهم.
In the country once known for its passive resignation,
في البلاد التي عُرفت يوما بانسحابها السلبي،
where, as bad as things got,
حيث، مهما ساءت الأمور،
only four percent expressed their opinion to a public official,
أربع في المئة فقط يعبرون عن رأيهم لمسؤول حكومي،
today 90 percent tell us
اليوم يخبرنا 90 بالمئة
that if there's a problem in their community,
بأنه إذا يكون هناك مشكلة في مجتمعهم المحلي
it's up to them to fix it.
الأمر متروك لهم لحلها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And three-fourths
وثلاثة أرباع
believe they not only have the responsibility,
يعتقدون أنهم لا يملكون المسؤولية فحسب،
but the power to make change.
بل أيضا القوة لإحداث التغيير.
And this empowerment
وهذا التمكين
also applies to women,
ينطبق أيضا على النساء،
whose role in the revolts
الذين دورهم في الثورات
cannot be underestimated.
لا يمكن الاستهانة به.
They were doctors and dissidents,
كنّ طبيبات ومعارضات
artists and organizers.
وفنانات ومنظمات.
A full third of those who braved tanks and tear gas
ثلث كامل من أولائك الذين واجهوا الدبابات والغاز المسيل للدموع
to ask or to demand liberty and justice in Egypt
ليسألوا ويطلبوا الحرية والعدالة في مصر
were women.
كانوا نساءا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now people have raised some real concerns
الآن أثار الناس بعض المخاوف الحقيقية
about what the rise of Islamist parties means for women.
حول ماذا يعني صعود الأحزاب الإسلامية للنساء.
What we've found about the role of religion in law
ما وجدناه حول دور الدين في القانون
and the role of religion in society
ودور الدين في المجتمع
is that there's no female consensus.
هو أنه لا يوجد إجماع أنثوي.
We found that women in one country
وجدنا أن النساء في بلد واحد
look more like the men in that country
يشبهون أكثر الرجال في ذلك البلد
than their female counterparts across the border.
من نظرائهم الإناث عبر الحدود.
Now what this suggests
الآن ما يوحي به ذلك
is that how women view religion's role in society
هو كيفية رؤية النساء لدور الدين في المجتمع
is shaped more by their own country's culture and context
يتشكل أكثر عبر ثقافة بلدهم نفسه وسياقه
than one monolithic view
من رؤية مُوَحَّدة
that religion is simply bad for women.
مفادها أن الدين ضار ببساطة للنساء.
Where women agree, however,
لكن ما يتفق عليه النساء
is on their own role,
هو حول دورهن نفسه
and that it must be central and active.
وهو الذي يجب أن يكون محوريا ونشيطا.
And here is where we see the greatest gender difference within a country --
وهنا حيث نرى أكبر فرق بين الجنسين داخل بلد --
on the issue of women's rights.
حول قضية حقوق المرأة.
Now how men feel about women's rights
الآن كيف يشعر الرجال حول حقوق المرأة
matters to the future of this region.
يهم مستقبل المنطقة.
Because we discovered a link
لأننا اكتشفنا رابطا
between men's support for women's employment
بين دعم الرجال لعمل المرأة
and how many women are actually employed
وكم تُشغّل في الحقيقة من إمرأة
in professional fields in that country.
في المجالات المهنية في تلك الدولة.
So the question becomes,
إذن السؤال يصبح،
What drives men's support for women's rights?
ماذا يدفع دعم الرجال لحقوق المرأة؟
What about men's views of religion and law?
ماذا عن رؤى الرجال للدين والقانون؟
[Does] a man's opinion
[هل] أن رأي الرجل
of the role of religion in politics
في دور الدين في السياسة
shape their view of women's rights?
يحدد نظرتهم لحقوق المرأة؟
The answer is no.
الجواب هو لا.
We found absolutely no correlation,
لم نجد قطعا أي صلة،
no impact whatsoever,
وأي تأثير أيا كان،
between these two variables.
بين هذان المتغيران.
What drives men's support for women's employment
ما يدفع دعم الرجال لعمل المرأة
is men's employment,
هو عمل الرجل
their level of education
ومستوى تعليمهم
as well as a high score
إضافة إلى درجة مرتفعة
on their country's U.N. Human Development Index.
لمؤشر الأمم المتحدة للتنمية البشرية الخاص بدولتهم.
What this means
ما يعني ذلك
is that human development,
هو أن التنمية البشرية
not secularization,
وليس العلمنة
is what's key to women's empowerment
هي مفتاح تمكين المرأة
in the transforming Middle East.
في الشرق الأوسط المتحول.
And the transformation continues.
ويستمر التحول.
From Wall Street to Mohammed Mahmoud Street,
من وول ستريت لشارع محمد محمود،
it has never been more important
لم تكن أبدا أكثر أهمية
to understand the aspirations
فهم طموحات
of ordinary people.
الناس العاديين.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)